[Music]
[Applause]
okay we're on homework six which you're
gonna do today before you get here
tomorrow okay so I'm gonna finish
homework six with you then I've been
trying to think it's not good for you to
have known the gardener for a whole year
and then come back and you're gonna
forget everything actually tomorrow
you're gonna forget everything so I have
a suggestion every time I do a retreat
which is the next one is Thailand end of
December right judgment end of December
what did 8 to 15 of December if you're
tired of snow or cold in your country
come to Thailand
very a lot of Russians there at that
time actually there are I don't know why
I guess it's an easy flight or something
and a lot of Europeans Germans like the
Spanish people Austrians and there's
also a lot of people from Asia there
obviously Malaysia JP Singapore
Indonesia Vietnam other countries okay
so you're quite welcome to come it's a
beautiful beautiful place talk to
Jasmine she's here she's running it I
think there's very little room I think
it's 500 people something
so anyway it'll be cool I mean warm
and we're at the beach and it's a
beautiful place okay so I'll then during
that lamium I will do in the garden a
broadcast or something okay so in
general we're not gonna maybe broadcast
we don't know yet but the guard you know
I'll do a class seven okay
from Thailand then in so you have to
watch okay and there's no good time zone
because we all live around the world so
if you're asleep you can see that
recording if you're asleep during the
class you can see the recording then
that'll be homework seven homework eight
will be at Diamond Mountain in April and
we'll be doing alarm room which dates
anybody Tim look it up yeah and you're
welcome to come back and we'll be doing
Lum room we'll be doing lots of
retreatment okay
and that'll be homework a and then
Guadalajara
yeah are you nodding okay I don't forget
parties naughty where he's in shock you
ain't getting shocked are you nodding
okay July I think what's a dates in
April April 12 to 21st here okay and we
will broadcast homework a and then nine
will be from Guadalajara and
the beautiful leg Jalapa well you love
[Laughter]
pachala
okay Chapala
japan and that's a beautiful leg it's
the largest lake and makes the core
right it's very similar to the Pacific
Ocean at level five
okay you can't see the end of it down
near Scorpion Island or something so
you're welcome to come to that it's a
beautiful place
Guadalajara is a Garden City we can go
there any time of the year if you look
at if you look on the internet it's a
Fahrenheit okay I don't know what's a
centigrade but it's 70 degrees all year
it's different like three degrees or
something so it's probably one of the
most beautiful climates in the world
Garden City so welcome to come there
it's a beautiful city I would like to
live there someday if I wasn't committed
to other places and then I'll so that'll
be homework 9 right and then we need to
do 10 from Sedona so we'll have in the
garden at teaching in Sedona for a day
or two okay
somewhere in there okay we'll just have
to figure it out like we're doing in
November 16 and 17 18 16 17 18 in Sedona
if you have time come Sedonas built for
tourists there's 10,000 people that
they're six million tourists every year
so Sedona is a big hotel and they have
cheap hotels called Tim's house
[Laughter]
[Music]
or a time filter right Phil he has
the biggest hotel in Rimrock and you're
welcome to come for that
this November we'll be doing a special
book called the angel debates the devil
and it's about the bad part of your mind
and the good part of your mind so Elmo
doesn't understand because her mind is
all good but other people have a bad
part and good parts and they debate so
the bad part in this case is wrong ideas
about meditation and wrong ideas about
emptiness and that part is fighting with
the good part which is correct ideas
about meditation or correct ideas about
emptiness so they have a fight and this
is a beautiful book written by the first
pension mama loss on Chuckie Jensen he
passed he was almost a hundred years old
1567 to 1662 if i'm not mistaken and
something like that one of the greatest
lamas of all time and very funny nama
and very brilliant book and so we're
gonna be doing that in it Sedona okay
and me and then we'll broadcast a tenth
homework of Nagant you know okay and
then you'll be ready for so every other
month or something you'll get some kind
of new gardener okay at your house
and then welcome back here in November
know October Tim's gonna look at the
dates 2019 inshallah what's inshallah
God willing okay like if we all survive
third to the 12th of October the
gardener - and we'll do five min ago
Janis okay and that will enable me to
stay on schedule and it will give you
dose of negara every few months okay so
you don't forget everything and tomorrow
people have asked me if I could do a
review of the whole week and try to tie
it together so we'll do that tomorrow
okay and today we have to go fast okay
we have to finish homework six which you
are working on tonight and taking a quiz
on tomorrow morning so the last question
is during your meditation did you think
about all the things you left here and
forgot to pack I'm just gonna review
where we've been so far in homework 6 we
started homework 6 yesterday the first
one was a question about the yarn
strings and the sweater okay when you
make a sweater from strings of yarn is
the sweater in the strings of yarn
already and we'll say no I don't see any
sweater in the strings of yarn but if
there's no potential for the sweater in
the strings of yarn then a sweater could
pop out of anything out of pizza okay
like because pizza also has no potential
for a sweater if there's not some kind
of potential for sweater insider threat
of yarn then then sweater can pop out of
a pizza okay because it's the same all
right so there must be some kind of
sweater in the yarn but then you have a
problem
then it doesn't have to make a sweater
because the sweater is already in the
urine okay and if it's not in New York
then how's the sweater going to come out
of the yarn maybe it will come out of
pizza okay all right
then are we just playing with words
no are we just goofing around mostly but
the point is there's something wrong
with stuff there's it's a little
impossible what's happening in my life
is impossible
so where are things really come from
we're doing parrisha we're investigating
you know what maybe investigations
better I think
then examination we're trying to figure
out well if it's not the way I thought
it was weather what's going on okay your
mind creates threads of yarn and then
later your mind creates a sweater okay
and really they both have to come
through your mind and the only way to
get a sweater in that scenario if that's
true the only way to get a sweater is to
to share clothing with the poor to to
help people who need clothing okay like
that okay so it's not just some
philosophy if you studied the gardener
correctly it will make you more generous
person in a more ethical person if you
understand emptiness you become more
ethical and more generous if you don't
understand emptiness you become a
philosopher and you get hired in a major
university okay
just kidding all those university
scholars I you can make fun of me too
okay okay six point second question all
right
then the guy gave a weird idea which was
in India at the time that the seed never
goes away he just puts on new clothes
okay the apple tree seed looks like a
seed for a while and then without
becoming a resolved he just puts on tree
clothes so the tree was always there in
this seat okay and that's one idea of
where the world came from there's
another idea by the way where the world
came from that was popular in Tibet
before Buddhism and that was that a if I
get it right a male monkey met a female
demon and they had sex the monkey and
the spirit had sex and people came up
and yaks and houses then okay you laugh
but what's your story from your country
okay
all right no that was a very serious if
you make fun of that monkey and Tibet
you're in trouble
no you they might execute your okay all
right
[Music]
question two okay so question two we
covered question three to was about the
seed changing clothes the seed remains
the seed it just puts on the outer
appearance we call number manifestation
of a tree and the punchline the gardener
kind of goes he takes a cheap shot we
call hitting the other guy in the place
where you're not supposed to hit him
down here he goes because the other guy
made a mistake he used one bad adverb
called really that seed doesn't go into
a tree it's really just the seed all the
time and it changes its outer appearance
so you think it's a tree but the tree
was always there indistinct and
sometimes the seed where the tree and
sometimes the seat takes the tree are
okay really
that's what's really happening and then
the gardener we call cheap shot he hits
the guy in the illegal place and he says
really really real cops will result go
home go home now I don't want to talk to
you okay
there's no real cause there's no real
reason okay that the cause with the tree
in it already that doesn't come from you
doesn't exist and the cause that changed
his clothes into a tree and became a
result also doesn't exist really so
don't give me the really if you give me
the really he doesn't really talk about
the problem with the idea he just
criticizes to one word you know don't
give me this really crowd excuse me now
then
my policeman is here stop don't give me
that stuff okay Homer question three
right which we covered already the guy
says look there is some potential in
seeds why because you don't get butter
from sesame seeds and you don't get
sesame oil by milking a cow okay so
there must be something in the scene
that's natural to the scene okay and
what do we think oh this is difficult
this one's difficult he says when you
say that you when you say when you give
me those two examples okay why you give
me two examples well I thought it might
be more clear you don't get sesame oil
from milking a cow and you don't get
butter by crushing sesame seeds I'm just
trying to make it more clear and then
the gardener says so kind of your first
your second example is making your first
example more clear right and he said
yeah and then he said so we can say the
truth of the first example depends on
the truth of the second example yeah in
that case this is all dependent right
yeah well if it's dependent it's not
natural right yeah if it's not natural
then the sesame oils not in the sesame
seed from the beginning right because
you can't be dependent and be natural at
the same time okay the existence of
sesame oil and a sesame seed cannot
depend on anything else it cannot depend
I'm thinking about milk okay thinking
about the sesame oil and the sesame seed
should not depend on thinking about
and butter and if it does depend on
thinking about milk and butter then it's
not natural okay in the sea okay got it
that's a very difficult one if you think
it's difficult for me to explain you
should have seen me with the book okay
now I want to show you something cute
okay you guys ready with those two
images I sent you so I'm working through
this idea this it's quite difficult this
idea is quite difficult okay
and this and some later ideas in the
second chapter which we're about to get
to depend on the difference on the word
lei lei means karma or lei means act I'm
sorry
action okay an action like you hit
somebody or you kiss somebody or this is
karma this is an action and then the
Guardian is gonna play with the
difference between an act and an action
okay
I don't know what it is in Chinese and I
don't care you figure it out okay act
and action okay two different words very
similar words okay so I'm struggling
with this okay I'm really struggling
with this or you know the the milk and
the butter somehow it depends on the the
sesame and the sesame all it depends on
the milk and the butter okay to think of
sesame and sesame oil it helps to think
about milk and butter and how they're
similar and how they're not similar
compare and contrast okay
now are you ready you guys so here's the
original text okay you have a partner
dearly whopper I'm not okay anyway
though there's a word in the second line
the first word in the second line says
mom which is L a.m.
in Tibetan and it means pop pop okay and
it's clearly L a.m.
right Nick we agree the boss of our
input project yeah yeah it's obviously L
a.m. okay and there's about 20 of those
in in this section L AM s and it was
carved that way and it's wrong okay so
for 350 years it's been carved wrong and
no one noticed which is frightening
because it's the meaning changes
completely
what's laymen and what's lan mean got it
so I can just see Tony Lama he writes a
book he finishes it he gives it to the
Carver the Carver's who don't speak who
cannot read or write
they just carve because they're carving
backwards and they're carving reverse in
Reverse they can't read they're like a
machine that takes the word and switches
it around you see they're carving and
they made 20 mistakes in like two pages
okay and I can see Tony Lama getting the
block you know and he's like oh my god
you know you can't change it now which
is the good thing but it's a bad thing
also I could just see him trying to not
get angry
I can I can really appreciate it and
he's trying to be a good example like
that's okay
he probably was fundraising to recall
those pages okay then he probably went
on retreat and he forgot about it
understand what I'm saying so the
problem is this one is almost understand
you can almost understand it's a little
strange but on the garden is strange so
you're like oh and the gardener must
have had a bad day this is really weird
this sentences are really weird you know
okay but he's a weird guy you know so I
translated it with the wrong word for
two days I think it was Tuesday and
Wednesday or something then then
suddenly I realized they're all wrong
okay
then the next day I realize half of them
are wrong and half of them I read okay
going every every woodblock has the same
problem okay
although I have three versions of the
woodblock three versions of tony romo
they're all wrong
okay which means somebody nobody noticed
since you three three four hundred fifty
years anyway
that's our job okay question for which
we already covered is you know the
Guardian is a great arguer but is he
really using the buddha's own speech and
I covered that I gave you a separate
reading I translated a big piece of some
copper for you you can answer that
question I don't need to go over it
of course he's directly using the Buddha
in the gardener and you if you're smart
if you did all your homework you can see
the gardener's structure in the Sutra
you can see he's following Buddha's own
structure his didn't write the book by
himself he's
he's following the Buddhist structure
and you can see it in the reading and I
gave you okay so that's question four
I think now we're on to missing and we
talked about last part of chapter one we
talked about what it means to be natural
okay what it means to be natural it's
inside the thing already nobody put it
there okay nobody put it there
okay nobody puts sweetness in sugar okay
right
that's just sugar that feeling about
sugar nobody made sugar sweet sweetness
is natural inside the sugar that's the
essence of wrong thinking that's the
essence of wrong thinking you made sugar
sweet you made peace round that's a
famous Buddhist thing who made peace
round come on
peas are just around when you say blood
is just blood you have wrong thinking
okay look guess not nobody made Peas
round peas are round no you just made a
mistake okay that's a sign that you
believe in a nature natural you made
peace around okay so they could get off
your plate easier when you're a kid and
fall on the floor so you don't have to
eat them probably that's the past karma
okay I understand who made needle-sharp
who made roses with the thorn shark who
made the this is a famous Buddhist
question peace and Rose thorns who made
Rose thorns sharp you did
okay nothing's natural in the gardener's
world okay and the only way you can get
to Nirvana is to go to new guards in
this world okay got it
okay I don't have to talk about that
anymore now I can go to new stuff all
right here's a okay
here's an easy question you don't have
to think you just write down what gosh
love says okay and this is the
difference between the gardener and
other writers okay
nothing their gardener says is easy and
so coppa said if you want to know the
easy parts go to somebody off I just do
the hard parts you know so but sometimes
it's nice on the homework if something
is clear and easy so here's an on the
garden anon some copper none are your
question there are two big divisions of
emptiness and they relate to
understanding emptiness intellectually
and having your direct experience of
emptiness which are different things
right please give the names of the first
two chapters of wisdom and connect them
to this division okay how do they
connect to this division okay here is
the answer just so you can understand
one answer today emptiness is divided
into the emptiness of the person and the
emptiness of things okay then in
parentheses in your answer it's gonna
say which can include the parts of the
person which can include the parts of
the person things can include can
include the parts of the person okay got
it
and in fact it classically does
you might even argue that there's no
other kind of emptiness of things but
that's another story okay which one of
these two do you see when you see
emptiness directly for the first time
the emptiness of people the empty by the
way it doesn't have to be humans right
it could be bugs or you know okay snakes
and by the way if you want to be precise
you don't say you see the emptiness of
the person when you see emptiness
directly the first time you see the
emptiness of a certain person which is
always yourself okay if you're pehla
pehla you see Palmas emptiness if you're
Annie use the onions emptiness you see
the first time okay all right but when
you're teaching this di program in Johor
Bahru that beautiful city on the river
which kind of emptiness is easier for
your audience to start with things okay
use a pan use an aspirin okay use
something like that okay so if you're in
the gardener and you want to write two
chapters and one chapters about the
emptiness of things and one chapters
about the emptiness of people which one
would you put first chap what
yeah no not direct perception by the way
if we're having a direct perception
while we're studying the Gardena we
can't see the book right we talked about
that so yeah he should do things first
and he does in his examination of
conditions conditions okay you could say
causes that's okay you can say factors
that's okay
but the first chapter is called I'm
starting like investigation Co Co Co Co
ah
he likes that too
I like the word investigation now so the
earlier homeworks are always gonna be
different from the later homers cuz
Geshe Michael changes things okay
invest investigation of conditions okay
it's the first chapter and it's talking
about the emptiness of things okay got
it
then you can predict the second chapter
yeah it must be talking about the
emptiness of people and a convenient way
to talk about the emptiness of people is
to talk about how people move how do
they come how do they go who's going
what's happening is it coming from me is
it even possible that people can be
going and coming in the way we always
thought and the answer is not possible
second husband in the kitchen not
possible okay the way you always thought
people go and people come I'll give you
an easy example okay but he doesn't have
any easy examples when I go towards the
door what's really happening yeah my
mind projects that a door of this size
and then my mind projects a door of this
size and then my mind projects the door
at this size and then my mind projects
that are this size okay and then when I
come
yeah my mind projects the scientist my
mind projects this size my mind purchase
well how come I never noticed that
geshe-la because it's 65 per second well
how can you perceive how who understood
that anyone who meditates well okay
that's why we're doing line stands
before in the gardener if you meditate
well you you will see the seeds opening
okay you can see one day you'll go oh my
god
gosh la was right you know you're gonna
go like this
oh yeah I'm so glad I went to time run
it wasn't a waste of money you know got
it so we're only a person who meditates
every day will ever see a seed opening
and and the door coming up okay got it
that's an easy explanation the gardener
has more difficult once he all right now
that was the easy question that's the
only kind of question you get in some
classes but not in the gardener so
question seven we okay on time Tim
can we take a break at 10:30 and then
start the presentation okay okay let me
speed through the whole Homer hmm what
do some tomorrow how's that okay
I'm answering questions seven no okay in
the beginning of his discussion so we
just moved to chapter two
okay the easy question was the beginning
of chapter two which is an investigation
of going and coming okay
we're changing the subject from causes
to the action of going and coming okay
in the beginning of his discussion on
going and coming Tony Lamas says let's
agree on one thing
okay this is also an easy question okay
Tim that's perfect
then we take a pee-pee breakin these fun
things
okay Tony Lama says remember one thing
about this chapter okay which part of
this going and coming is the difficult
part okay that no gardener says that's
weird okay which part of going and
coming is so difficult you know which
part you're gonna say wow that's weird
must be coming from me okay here's the
part the gardener divides all going and
coming into past past I I went yesterday
or I came to the temple this morning
okay the past part then future part I'm
going to walk to the bathroom as soon as
geshe-la shut up okay so I walk to the
temple this morning past past walking
past going past coming okay and after
geshe-la stops this question
we're all gonna walk or run to the
bathroom okay
that's future going the gardener says
that's not so interesting that's not so
interesting I'm interested in now ing in
English ing go wing coming I'm not
interested in went and I'm not
interested in going to call I'm
interested what is going and what is
coming the gardener says there's a
reason I put ing s on the name of the
chapter we're gonna investigate what's
going in the present moment and what's
going in the future moment and since
we're on the subject and it would only
take a second to do homework question
eight let's just do it right away
the gardener has a problem with cold we
okay the gardener has a problem with go
wing okay so he says what is go wing you
know what is go wing when you put your
foot down okay ready do you walk like
this
the whole foot comes down at the same
moment or do you walk like which one
yeah
so which part of the foot is gone and
which part of foot is go gonna go which
part of the foot is gone the heel yeah
yeah so it's gonna go the heel is gone
right where's the line where's the going
this is somewhere under here
how how wide is this they said to me
they're gonna have attempted me there
you know how wide is to go in where's
the going okay here's the problem the
garden of love that stuff
you guys are loves that stuff okay when
you walk you don't go you go good bum
then when the car is down the bunk is
not down then the going must be
somewhere between but where does it
start and where the where is it finish
okay got it
there's a problem baby your mind is
making bigger door maybe there is no
good done get done got it
if something's wrong with the way you go
then
look here maybe it's coming out of your
mind okay got it
geshe-la why you waste time like that
I'm gonna go to the bathroom I'm not
gonna worry about this line if I worry
about this line you're gonna have water
inside the temple
okay don't don't make me worry about
some crazy things you know no but you
don't understand
the body that has to go to the bathroom
will die there's only so many peopie's
in your human body when you're born I
think you have I know you figured out
Timken a hundred thousand peepees okay
well I'm up to like ninety eight
thousand your year around sixty thousand
okay it's mileage on your rental car
right so you better figure out where
it's coming from
because we're in a race with death okay
peepee number hundred thousand come
first or or you figured this out because
if you don't figure out how this is
coming from your mind you will die okay
you must use the gardener on your body
change your body okay before you get too
old then it's too late
okay it's too late so we're kind of in a
race to the bathroom and also a race
against death got it we got understand
the gardener before this gets to him
okay and it will get all them okay those
of us who are over 40 we can tell you
it's like wait a minute Veronica and I
met each other when we're 16 we had a
crush for 48 years
it's 49 years but it goes like you're
like wow what happened I don't know we
were just in high school okay
so there's not time you gotta figure out
where where it's coming from where is
coming coming from where is going coming
from cuz that's the only way you can
change your body okay in the meantime we
still have to pee pee so take a break
and then we're gonna do the
impatiens right we're gonna do some real
out presentations okay and you can do
eight questions on your Homerton
okay and I'll do the last one tomorrow
yeah last one tomorrow
by the way tomorrow to do question 9
we're gonna go to a Sangha for a while
we're gonna go to my trailer for a while
okay all right bye
Go Go run flatfoot
[Music]